<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rails | Code Adventurer]]></title>
  <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/categories/rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-06T09:34:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://codeadventurer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Persa Zula]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[persa@persazula.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Rails with PostgreSQL locally]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/11/02/running-rails-with-postgresql-locally"/>
    <updated>2013-11-02T13:18:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/11/02/running-rails-with-postgresql-locally</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a few issues installing Rails for the first time with PostgreSQL locally, and since the problems I was having as a newbie in both were not well-documented on the internet, I thought I&rsquo;d post a rundown of what happened and how I fixed it. <!-- more --></p>

<h3>Installing pgsql with home-brew</h3>

<p>This topic has been covered exhaustively on the web, but the way I did it was to run:</p>

<p><code>
$ brew update
$ brew install postgresql
</code>
Then, I followed the rest of the directions in the terminal to finish my install, and to install the pg gem.</p>

<p><strong><em>Big thing of note:</em></strong> If you are not sure you followed all the directions, and you&rsquo;re getting crazy errors, and you&rsquo;ve already closed your terminal, all is not lost!</p>

<p>You can run <code>brew info postgresql</code> to see the instructions again and double check.</p>

<h3>Fixing your broken PG Connection in Rails</h3>

<p>I decided to start my first rails project with pgsql, because I wanted to give it a try and after using sqlite3 a few times already, I was ready to graduate to something I could actually deploy on Heroku.</p>

<p>So I created my brand-new rails app by running this command in my terminal:</p>

<p><code>rails new blogger -d postgresql</code></p>

<p>Everything looked gravy, until I loaded up <a href="http://localhost:3000">http://localhost:3000</a> and got the big red Rails error with something I did not understand:</p>

<p><code>PG::ConnectionBad (FATAL:  role "blogger" does not exist
):</code></p>

<p>So I found that after doing that, I did some research and found that I needed to run the rake task to actually set up the databases. That&rsquo;s fine by me! So I ran this in my terminal:
<code>rake db:create:all</code></p>

<p>Then, my terminal blew up and the error I would get would be:
<code>FATAL:  role "blogger" does not exist</code></p>

<p>Not knowing much about this, I spent some time searching and found out that I needed to create a new user named the same thing as the user in my <code>database.yml</code> file in the Rails app. Mine happens to be <code>blogger</code>, so I then went into my terminal and ran the following command:
<code>createuser -s -r blogger</code></p>

<p>Then, I ran this command again, this time successfully: <code>rake db:create:all</code></p>

<p>After doing this, and restarting my Rails server, I went back to <a href="http://localhost:3000">http://localhost:3000</a> and I was happily riding the Rails!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
