<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Code Adventurer]]></title>
  <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-06T15:31:51-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://codeadventurer.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Persa Zula]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[persa@persazula.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Turtles & Mentors]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/10/04/learning-from-a-mentor"/>
    <updated>2013-10-04T20:41:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/10/04/learning-from-a-mentor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our most recent project at gSchool, called <a href="http://tutorials.jumpstartlab.com/projects/sales_engine.html">SalesEngine</a>, was quite a stretch for a lot of us in the class. <!-- more --> Beyond the complexity of EventReporter, we had not had any time to recover from that project, overview the lessons learned, and reinforce the most important concepts from from the project. Instead, we jumped right into the next project, some of us without even having touched EventReporter, others with only half of the project completed.</p>

<p>With our new pairs, we dove into the requirements. The project looked massive at first glance, but slowly we started to follow through the requirements (with very handy method and class name requirement) and made progress.</p>

<p>Our progress skidded to a halt once we hit the relationships piece. Although I understand databases, foreign key relationships and how to get my data in and out of MySQL using PHP, I had no idea how to get my objects to pass around stored information to each other in Ruby.</p>

<p>My partner was equally confused. We stepped through an explanation with Jorge on Friday, and spent the weekend putting it together. We took the approach of calling our main interface class, SalesEngine, from every other piece of the program, so that we could reach through SalesEngine down into our data storage collections (called Repositories in this project). Apparently, we didn&rsquo;t understand the Object Model, but then again we haven&rsquo;t talked much about the Object Model except for the fact that everything is an object.</p>

<p>Having completed our relationships piece exactly the wrong way, we were on to building the pieces of business intelligence into the program. Suddenly we had to actually make our idea of the relationships make sense in our heads to get these pieces working, and suddenly everything seemed to be running in circles. On Monday, our instructor Katrina helped us understand where we went wrong, and showed us how to pass through a copy of SalesEngine (by using <code>self</code>) to each repository, and in turn to each individual piece of the program.</p>

<p>We spent a good deal of time of Monday refactoring our relationship model, and finally were back to our original issue: how do we grab and compare data stored in different places in the application?</p>

<p>After some nudging and help from various instructors, we started to understand how things were supposed to work. On Tuesday, with two days to go, we got to building the first few pieces of business intelligence. I sat down to read the piece on the first item, and this is what my psuedocode looked like:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='ruby'><span class='line'> <span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">test_it_can_find_the_merchant_with_the_most_x_revenue</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">engine</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="no">SalesEngine</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">new</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s2">&quot;./test/fixtures&quot;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># find all invoices by merchant_id</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># then find each invoice id for the merchant_id</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># use invoice_id to call invoice_items that match</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># compare these invoice_id&#39;s to tranactions invoice_id </span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># only use the ids that have result == success</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># take the quantitiy of the items &amp; multiply by the price</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># process the price into BigDecimal (don&#39;t use Float)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># store that in an array</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1"># sort the array on .sort or some similar array method</span>
</span><span class='line'> <span class="k">end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>In the end, this pseudocode actually didn&rsquo;t help me out at all. It wasn&rsquo;t until I stepped back and read through
all of the requirements that I realized that starting at the top of the list would not get us to the final endpoint. In order to report the top <code>x</code> merchants based on revenue, we would have to create helper classes associated with invoices and transactions.</p>

<p>Eventually, by the end of the night we had tested and created methods for our individual <code>Merchant</code>, <code>Invoice</code>, <code>Transaction</code>, and <code>MerchantRepository</code> classes to help us get some sort of response from the system.</p>

<p>But there was a bug. And that it turns out that wherever there is one bug, there are many more in hiding. It was 4:30, and the instructors were leaving for the day, and we were stuck.</p>

<p>Thankfully, <a href="https://twitter.com/corylanou">Cory LaNou</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/levicook">Levi Cook</a>, founders and developers at <a href="http://www.supportlocal.com/">SupportLocal</a>, offer their time and energy for help on Tuesday evenings to gSchool students.</p>

<p>Cory spent four hours with my partner and I that night, showing us how to debug a program, and exploring with us where things were going wrong. Besides various errors that we have made using core methods, we also discovered that our test data set was completely useless without our foreign keys matching up. It took us that fours hours to get two tests to pass.</p>

<p>I couldn&rsquo;t believe how much time he had spent with us, going around in circles, walking us through debugging, and helping us find the issues in our program. I would love it if every mentor out there were as patient as Cory.</p>

<p>Although in the end we did not finish SalesEngine, I believe the lessons we learned from Cory about debugging, and the persistence needed when tracking down issues, were monumental, and very important to the success of our future projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning from the Community]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/29/learning-from-the-community"/>
    <updated>2013-09-29T18:40:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/29/learning-from-the-community</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This past week of gSchool, we got our first outside-of-the-classroom introductions to the Ruby community by attending <a href="http://rockymtnruby.com/">Rocky Mountain Ruby Conf</a><!-- more -->, and also by having a personal session with <a href="https://github.com/wayneeseguin">Wayne E. Seguin</a>, the original creator of RVM.</p>

<p>Wayne taught us a few important lessons, but the most important advice I heard is to know yourself, and to know how to deal with yourself. As a similar work-a-holic, when I am at home (aka: not in gSchool, where work-a-holicism is somewhat of a neccessity), I tend to spend hours learning new things after work, and ignoring my friends and family. Although great for keeping up with the current tech trends, this tends to wear on my personal relationships. To combat this, Wayne has set aside the 5pm to 8pm block of time as &ldquo;family time&rdquo;, and has alerted all of his friends, the open source projects he works on, and his colleagues of this rule. He sticks to it, and with this expectation, he does not let anyone down. His family knows his focus is on them during that time, and his co-collaborators respect that he is away and unavailable to work during that time of day.</p>

<p>At Rocky Mountain Ruby, I learned a lot about the community. Aside from the stickers, soft tshirts, and good food, the presenters where really knowledgable about their topics. I have attended conferences before, but I have never been to a conference with only one track. This was interesting to me, because although I didn&rsquo;t have enough practical knowledge on the subject, I was forced to hear about threading, Go (the language), and 17 databases that I&rsquo;ve never heard of before, I listened throughout the presentations and was able to learn something about the subject. Coming out of the conference, I was amazed at how much I had understood about every presentation. It goes to show that if you listen and try to understand, you will learn.*</p>

<p>Learning from the community, regardless of whether it is the Ruby community, or another community in general, is a very interesting experience. If you listen carefully, you hear about the triumphs, the losses, the intersections of people and pride, and the lessons that others have learned. I&rsquo;ve found that it is wise to listen hard during these anecdotes, because those that wore this path before us have made mistakes (or discoveries) that we can benefit from knowing, and hopefully apply to our own individual journeys.</p>

<p><strong>*Pro-tip:</strong> Sit in the front during conferences and presentations. If you have any sense of shame left in you, you won&rsquo;t be as compelled to whip open your laptop or check your phone. And without distractions, there is only one thing left to do: listen to the presentation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning is Effin' Hard]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/20/learning-is-effin-hard"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T09:04:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/20/learning-is-effin-hard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two days into building Event Reporter (you can find the project guidelines <a href="http://tutorials.jumpstartlab.com/projects/event_reporter.html">here</a>), I was flummoxed. <!-- more -->I&rsquo;d only been programming in Ruby for a little over a week, and we were diving head-first into test-driven development, while programming our first project without any training wheels. I came to Katrina, our super-heroine, molecular-biologist-turned-programmer instructor, and showed her my codebase. I was trying hard to separate concerns, build different classes, and keep every class and every test in its own file. This was starting to confuse me, and I was starting to lose sight of how to connect all the pieces back to one another. She took a few looks at what I had done, and asked me to <code>rm -rf</code> everything. All of it.</p>

<p>I looked at her in disbelief, explained that this was hours worth of work (even though really it looked like there wasn&rsquo;t much there)… and then complied. And cried a little inside.</p>

<p>Starting with a blank slate, and just two files this time &ndash; one for all of my classes, and one for all of my tests &ndash; I looked at the requirements and started building from the first test case, &ldquo;Happy Path&rdquo;. I had one day left before the project was done, and I was starting to stress out. Why was this so hard? Every class I&rsquo;ve ever taken, every passion I have pursued, has come easily to me. I can memorize insane facts, make connections between farming and management, lead groups, organize events, cook awesome organic meals, fix bicycles, juggle, live in yurts… and this project is the thing that is going to show me who is boss? I couldn&rsquo;t handle it.</p>

<p>With every hour that went by, as some tests failed and somewhere along the way, a few passed, I kept getting more and more frustrated. I started to doubt being ever able to call myself a web developer in the past. If I couldn&rsquo;t get this basic project to work, how was I going to move on to the next one? At 8:30pm the night before the project was due, I had only four methods that could pass tests. I shut my laptop, realized there was no way I could finish in time, and went to sleep.</p>

<p>I awoke at 3:30am from dreams where I was expertly solving Event Reporter, one passing test at a time, and quickly got out my laptop to try to recreate what was I was programming in my dreams. I cranked out the tests, and slowly started realizing that all of it was gibberish. Dream-state me wasn&rsquo;t actually expertly solving anything, although it seemed like it. But, I was awake anyway, so I hit the gym at 4am, got through my workout, and decided to come to gSchool early and try again.</p>

<p>I worked through my code for a little while before Katrina showed up (she has some crazy schedule where she goes to bed at 8pm and gets to work at 5am), and helped me back away from the ledge of jumping off of the programmer cliff. She looked at me and said, &ldquo;Learning is elfin&#8217; hard.&rdquo; Coming from a molecular biologist, I must have actually believed her, because an hour and  half later, after talking through my code and my struggles, I started to feel better about the project (even through I was still nowhere near done).</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still not done today, but I have an idea of where I&rsquo;m going. Talking with Katrina, Jorge, and Franklin during different pieces, and various colorful feelings ranging from rage to anger to depression to self-hate (gosh, I never knew programming could bring out so much in me) really helped me understand that all of us at gSchool are used to being good at things. And a lot of us are struggling &mdash; not just with the syntax and the TDD mindset, but also with this ego-crushing feeling of failure.</p>

<p>And then I have to remind myself that today is day 10 of gSchool. And there are still five and a half months to go. Two weeks ago, I had never written a test for one of my programs. I&rsquo;ve learned a lot in this time &mdash; not only about Ruby, but about myself, my classmates, and the human spirit.</p>

<p>Thank you, gSchool, for showing me that learning a new programming language can be one of the most amazing things to teach me about myself.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in the spiderweb of code I&rsquo;ve been building for this project, you can find my codebase on <a href="https://github.com/pzula/event_reporter">GitHub</a>. Feel free to let me know what you think, either about the code, or about my journey, or about similar experiences you&rsquo;ve had in the comments section.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: The Carolina Morning Zen Office Floor Desk]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/10/review-carolina-morning-zen-office"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T22:02:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/10/review-carolina-morning-zen-office</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous post, I spoke about getting your computer ready for you to work, but I didn&rsquo;t spend much time talking about getting <strong>yourself</strong> ready to work. In a series of posts, I will cover tools beyond your computer that can help you be a better developer.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As developers, we spend a lot of time at our computers. We obsess over the technical specifications of the newest laptop, and discuss the benefits and drawbacks of the newest library that was released, but we don&rsquo;t spend much time talking about how we &mdash; as human beings in physical bodies &mdash; interact with the tools of our trade.</p>

<p>Generally speaking, these days many programmers are working on powerful, lightweight laptops. The freedom of being able to work from anywhere &mdash; a coffee shop, an airport, or even sitting on the couch &mdash; has led many of us to ditch the notion of large, noisy computer towers in favor of the ultrabook.</p>

<p>As we put away our gargantuan computers of years past, we also traded in our ergonomic desk setups for hunched-over, strained-neck, cramped sitting styles in laps and on table-tops to use our primary tool of the trade. Gone are the keyboard trays, the gel-padded wrist protectors, and the $500 chairs.</p>

<p>The issue at hand is that laptop keyboards are attached to the screen of the laptop, which, when seated at a regular desk, forces the laptop user to look down. This posture consequently rounds the shoulders in wards towards the chest. Keeping the neck and shoulders in this unnatural position for hours at a time can lead to long-term injuries, including RSI (repetitive stress injury), nerve damage, migraines, and more. (For all of the potential risks, ask a professional chiropractor or musculoskeletal specialist).</p>

<p><img src="http://www.codeadventurer.com/images/laptop_positions.gif" alt="Three potential postures with a laptop" /></p>

<p>As you can see in the figure(1) above, there seems to be no decent way to achieve good posture while using a laptop without additional peripherals.</p>

<p>Enter <a href="http://www.zafu.net/">Carolina Morning Designs</a>* and the Japenese-inspired minimalist furniture that Linsi Deyo and her partner Patrick Clark offer for sale on their website. Linsi and Patrick have designed the <a href="http://www.zafu.net/zenoffice.html">Zen Office</a>, a desk that keeps you seated close to the floor and re-stacks your skeletal structure so that your back stays straight, your head is not bent over, and your arms are in a comfortable typing position.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.codeadventurer.com/images/zen_desk.jpg" alt="Using the Carolina Morning Designs Zen Office" /></p>

<p>This type of seating is called &ldquo;active sitting&rdquo;, as you engage the core muscles of your abdomen and back to help you stay seated. It is uncomfortable to take a slouched position at the Zen Office.</p>

<p>In addition to the floor position, it is also possible for the Zen Office to be repurposed in other ways. If you prefer to switch between sitting and standing, you can easily use the Zen Office along with a wireless keyboard and mouse to accomplish this.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.codeadventurer.com/images/zen_desk_sitting.jpg" alt="Using the Carolina Morning Designs Zen Office While Sitting" /></p>

<p>Having used a gamut of seating situations for computer work, ranging from cardboard-box standing desks, to $22 Ikea hacks for a standing desk, and even yoga balls for active sitting, I can say with confidence that I don&rsquo;t think I will ever need another desk besides the Carolina Mornings Design Zen Office. Since it breaks back down to two small packages, with no tools required for assembly, I can take it anywhere, and whenever I get tired in one position, I can quickly move to another.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.codeadventurer.com/images/zen_desk_standing.jpg" alt="Using the Carolina Morning Designs Zen Office While Standing" /></p>

<p>What sort of sitting and standing arrangements have you used for computer work? Do you alternate throughout the day, or just stay in one position?</p>

<hr />

<p>*I found Carolina Morning Designs while researching sleeping on the floor, as I have been living in a yurt again and in my packing for gSchool have refused to bring a mattress or purchase a new one. If you love sleeping on a firm surface, as I do, check out their modular platform bedframes and other minimalistic sleeping surfaces.</p>

<p>1: Griffin, Timothy, &ldquo;The Adaptive Laptop&rdquo;. October, 2001. Timothy Griffin, Industrial Design Program, The University of Calgary. <a href="http://tim.griffins.ca/writings/mdp-intro">http://tim.griffins.ca/writings/mdp-intro</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting a New Development Environment Up &amp; Running on Mac OSX]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/05/getting-a-new-development-environment-up-and-running-on-mac-osx"/>
    <updated>2013-09-05T21:14:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/05/getting-a-new-development-environment-up-and-running-on-mac-osx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Getting a new computer can be fun, but it also means a lot of work. Between running into bugs, new versions of software running amok, and documentation from various sources on the big, bad internet just not lining up, it can quickly go from being fun to just being plain frustrating.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>I had a few of those moments myself in the last couple days, so I thought I&rsquo;d share with other journeymen and women some of the core items I get set up on a new machine. Perhaps a few of the snippets may help you get out of a snag, or maybe you&rsquo;ll find a new tool to love.</p>

<h2>In a loose order of importance</h2>

<h3>Basic Apps</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>The very first thing I installed was <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred</a>. If you love Spotlight, go ahead and stick with it, but I love the flexibility of Alfred for getting around, doing math for me, and lots of other tasks that usually take more than two keystrokes.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/fx/#desktop">Firefox</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/browser/">Chrome</a>, to have browsers to test in. I primarily use Chrome in my daily work, and only every touch Safari for testing.</p></li>
<li><p>A few extensions for Firefox and Chrome include <a href="http://getpocket.com">Pocket</a> (for saving things to read later), <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/web-developer/">Web Developer Toolbar</a>, <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/firebug/?src=search">Firebug</a>, and <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/personal-blocklist-by-goo/nolijncfnkgaikbjbdaogikpmpbdcdef?hl=en">Personal Blocklist for Chrome</a> (this one helps me block anything by w3cschools.com, because most of the time, that site does not promote best practices)</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.evernote.com">Evernote</a> helps me keep track of everything &mdash; from grocery lists to bug fixes. Whenever I think of something, I can pop open Evernote, and be sure that when I need to come back to it, I can access it from anywhere. I love this app, and it&rsquo;s free!</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.skype.com">Skype</a> helps me keep in touch with other developers, friends, and family around the world.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Developer&rsquo;s choice</h3>

<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://www.sublimetext.com">Sublime Text 2</a> is my editor of choice. Although I know there are many proponents of Vi/Vim and other non-GUI editors, my focus right now is on learning to become a better programmer. I&rsquo;ll focus on learning those later. Here are my favorite Sublime Text 2 packages:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://docs.emmet.io/">Emmet</a></li>
<li><a href="http://net.tutsplus.com/articles/news/introducing-nettuts-fetch/">NetTuts Fetch</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tutsplus.com/lesson/lightning-fast-folder-and-file-creation/">Advanced New File</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tutsplus.com/lesson/sidebar-enhancements/">Sidebar Enhancements</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/SublimeLinter/SublimeLinter">Sublime Linter</a></li>
<li>I also enable Sublime to be opened from the command line (this is where the Vim users scoff).
Run this in your terminal: <code>ln -s "/Applications/Sublime Text 2.app/Contents/SharedSupport/bin/subl" /bin/subl
</code>   Now you will be able to open any file from the Terminal with <code>$ subl filename-here.html</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>You can use Sublime Text 2 as your Markdown editor for blog posts, but I prefer the immediate feedback of <a href="http://mouapp.com">Mou</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li>I find that I&rsquo;m often at the command line wanting to use Mou, but don&rsquo;t feel like going through the GUI to open a new file or the app itself, so I set up an alias in my <code>.bash_profile</code> as follows: <code>alias mou="open /Applications/Mou.app"</code>. Now whenever I <code>rake</code> a new post in Octopress, I can immediately open it with Mou without having to take my hands off the keyboard.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<h3>Terminal modifications</h3>

<ol>
<li><p>Speaking of the command line, I have a few little modifications I like to make to the Terminal in order to make it easier for me to use. Take what you want, leave what you don&rsquo;t.</p>

<ul>
<li>First, I update my Terminal theme. I personally like <a href="https://github.com/altercation/solarized">Solarized</a>, as it is easy on the eyes. <a href="http://noiseandheat.com/blog/2011/12/os-x-lion-terminal-colours/">Mac installation instructions here</a></li>
<li><p>A typical install of OS X won&rsquo;t create a <code>.bash_profile</code> for you. When you want to run functions from your command line, this is a must-have:</p>

<ul>
<li>Start up Terminal</li>
<li>Type <code>cd ~/</code> to go to your home folder</li>
<li>Type <code>touch .bash_profile</code> to create your new file.</li>
<li>Edit .bash_profile with your favorite editor (or you can just type <code>open -e .bash_profile</code> to open it in TextEdit.</li>
<li>Type <code>. .bash_profile</code> to reload .bash_profile and update any functions you add.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>I then update the Terminal to show the full path of where I am at. This helps me when I&rsquo;m working on programs that might have similar file names in different folders.</p>

<ul>
<li>In ~.bash_profile, add: <code>export PS1='\u@\H:\w$</code></li>
<li>Then restart bash</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>I also like my file listings to be colorful, so I add the following items to my <code>.bash_profile</code>:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>export CLICOLOR=1</code></li>
<li><code>export LSCOLORS=gxBxhxDxfxhxhxhxhxcxcx</code> (This color set works well with the Solarized bash theme)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<h3>Development environment</h3>

<p>Now that my basic tools are installed, I get into installing my development tools specific to Ruby and my <a href="http://gschool.it">gSchool</a> learning needs.</p>

<ol>
<li>I got my Ruby development environment all set up and worked through the nuances with <a href="http://twitter.com/kytrinyx">Katrina Owen</a> from Jumpstart Lab. <a href="http://tutorials.jumpstartlab.com/topics/environment/environment.html">Here are the updated instructions</a>, in great detail.</li>
<li>I also copied over my ssh key pairs from my old machine to ensure I could continue using them for my GitHub and Heroku accounts. Remember to copy permissions for all files in the folder as well!</li>
<li>I also go to my home directory and <code>mkdir</code> a Sites folder &mdash; this restores the functionality of the Sites folder that used to work in previous OSX versions. I like to store my web projects in there for easy access. I also tell Alfred about that folder so that it becomes indexed and searchable.</li>
<li>Finally, I alias my Ruby versions and I am ready to go!</li>
</ol>


<h2>After all that…</h2>

<p>I definitely recommend <a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/ht1553">creating a backup image of your machine</a> in this state, because it all takes a lot of work. Keep you image in a safe space, because you never know when you&rsquo;re going to need it!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On a Quest for Awesome]]></title>
    <link href="http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/02/on-a-quest-for-awesome"/>
    <updated>2013-09-02T17:41:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://codeadventurer.com/2013/09/02/on-a-quest-for-awesome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two summers ago, after forays into organic farming and yurt living, I found myself in a really cool position at the Ohio State University <a href="http://www.oardc.ohio-state.edu/amp/">Agricultural Ecosystem Management Program</a> <!-- more --> that combined many things I was passionate about: building usable web systems, building community, and local agriculture. I was helping  make changes to <a href="http://localfoodsystems.org">Local Food Systems</a>, a website that helps connect entreprenuers with the food system (and those who run it) to help spawn new businesses based on the stream of goods and services in that system. I was working in <a href="http://drupal.org">Drupal</a>, and helped guide user experience and user interface decisions and changes in the three months that I was there on a half-time contract.</p>

<p>When the end of August came, I was sad to find out that this awesome job could not become a full-time endeavor because there were no new grants for the project, and neither could my half-time contract be extended. That same week, I was contacted by an internal recruiter for <a href="http://fathomdelivers.com">Fathom</a>, a digital marketing and analytics agency closer to where I had just moved, and began the conversation of becoming a full time web developer there.</p>

<p>Within a few weeks I was working for Fathom, building a lot of frontends to landing pages and microsites that were mostly used in email marketing and pay-per-click campaigns. In my first few weeks at Fathom, the Twitter-sphere was abuzz about <a href="http://www.gschool.it">gSchool</a>, a 6 month web development program in Denver, Colorado. I checked out the website, read a little bit about it, and thought to myself, &ldquo;Wow, it&rsquo;d be so great to learn web development from the pros, but who has the time to spend 6 months not earning a paycheck?&rdquo; I was intrigued by Ruby and thought it would be great to learn someday, but I moved on, back to my frontends, and back to my spaghetti PHP.</p>

<p>During my year at Fathom, I started getting more interested in Ruby, Test Driven Development, and Agile methodology, but the work we were doing on the web development team was rigid. But we sold our products well, and we had jam-packed development schedules. There was no time to explore or implement the things I was reading about, the things that I so desperately wanted to learn.</p>

<p>I thought I could fit in new learning by starting a <a href="http://codeforamerica.org">Code for America</a> Brigade in my town, dubbed <a href="http://codeforsummitcounty.org">Code for Summit County</a>, and organizing an event for the <a href="http://ndoch.org">National Day of Civic Hacking</a> locally, called <a href="http://hackNEO.org">HackNEO</a>, (which brought together over 30 local developers, designers, park lovers, and community memeber to hack on park data). As I worked and organized, I realized that if I was going to continue to be a leader, my learning needed a serious turbo boost to propel me forward past the bad habits I had acquired through self-teaching and a lack of a programming mentor.</p>

<p>I started exploring the option of attending one of those developer bootcamps that I had heard about. I needed a time and a place to focus on learning, without interruption. I researched all of them, read what students had to say about them, and thought about applying to them. But I wasn&rsquo;t sure if I could do it. I had a life at home &ndash; three months (the average of these bootcamps) was a long time away from everything that needed my attention &ndash; family, chickens, my cat, my job…</p>

<p><strong>And then it all boiled down to making a pros and cons list.</strong></p>

<p>An honest, hard look at the opportunity cost, as well as the ways doing this now would pay off for the rest of my career, brought me to one conclusion: <strong>Just do it.</strong></p>

<p>My focus was being close to home, in Chicago or New York at the bootcamps available there, when suddenly, seemingly out of the blue, <a href="https://twitter.com/steveklabnik/">Steve Klabnik</a> tweeted an application deadline reminder for gSchool. I had been following Steve on Twitter for a while, but hadn&rsquo;t realized he was an instructor for <a href="http://jumpstartlab.com">Jumpstart Lab</a>, the company that runs gSchool. I took another hard look at gSchool, and completed the application. I didn&rsquo;t think I stood a chance.</p>

<p>Fast-forward to today, and here I am, writing this post in Denver, Colorado. Next week we start gSchool[1], the second class that gSchool will graduate, and my coding adventures will continue. I will have experienced mentors helping me understand the tough spots, pushing me to the next level, and helping me unlearn bad habits, learn a new language, and build the skills needed to bring to life the ideas that have been gnawing at me for years.</p>

<p>I plan to document the journey so that others may have a map to guide them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
